<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pattern of mercy. Opened in a sermon at St. Pauls, before the Right Honorable, the Lord Mayor, and the Lord General Monck: February 12. 1659. / By Tobias Conyers, minister at St. Ethelberts, London.</title>
            <author>Conyers, Tobias, 1628-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80396</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5994</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E774_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207295</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866353</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866353</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118624</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80396)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118624)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 118:E774[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pattern of mercy. Opened in a sermon at St. Pauls, before the Right Honorable, the Lord Mayor, and the Lord General Monck: February 12. 1659. / By Tobias Conyers, minister at St. Ethelberts, London.</title>
                  <author>Conyers, Tobias, 1628-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 30, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.I. and are to be sold at the Grey-hound in St. Pauls Church-yard. at the Crown in Popes-head Alley, and at the Elephant and Castle near Temple Barr,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata p. [14].</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb: 27 1659"; the date has been crossed out. "1659 Feb: 27".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke VI, 36 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Mercy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118624:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Pattern of Mercy. Opened in a SERMON AT S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> PAULS, BEFORE The Right Honorable, the Lord Mayor, AND THE Lord General Monck: February 12. 1659. By TOBIAS CONYERS, Miniſter at St. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelberts, London.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by M. I. and are to be ſold at the Grey-hound in St. Pauls Church-yard. at the Crown in Popes-head Alley, and at the Elephant and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle near Temple Barr, 1660.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118624:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118624:2"/>
            <head>The Authors Apology.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>WHen I entered upon the enſuing Diſcourſe in my private Meditations, I looked upon the complexion of the times, and conſidered the temper of the climate in which we live, and in a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion all rent and torn with differences in Opinions both Civil &amp; Religious, I thought nothing could be more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable then a propoſition of peace: But whilſt I</hi> ſpoke for peace, <hi>(ſuch was my unhappineſs)</hi> ſome men made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ready for battel. <hi>The giving of offence to any ſort of perſons, was a thing as far remote from any deſign or pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe of mine, as it is diſagreeable to my temper &amp; diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to be at ods with any man. And looking over theſe Papers which now I publiſh to the world, (if I may be permitted to judge in mine own caſe) I cannot but wonder from whence the great cry of the City aroſe, as if ſome</hi> Theudas, <hi>or</hi> Judas Galilaeus <hi>were riſen from the dead; being naturally averſe from the ſtarting of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny new Opinions, and far enough from having any thing extraordinary in me either to create or make me the head of any new ſect or faction: It is confeſſed the</hi> 12th. <hi>of</hi> Fehruary <hi>was a critical day, and all circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces concurred to render me unacceptable: What I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118624:3"/> 
               <hi>in my ſelf, was nothing; but that I ſhould ſo much as accidentally occaſion any reflection upon that noble Gentleman, the Lord Mayor, (whom all men muſt needs judge both too great and too wiſe to concern him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in any thoughts or meditations of minds) troubled me not a little; it's true, I had been often ſoliciting my Lord for diſmiſſion; and that he took this occaſion to do it, was ſo far leſs diſpleaſing to me, as it was ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory unto others; for having ſerved his Lordſhip for himſelf without any mercenary propoſals and expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I could not in the leaſt be diſ-ſatisfied with any thing that did but ſeem either to ſupport or vindicate his Lordſhips Honor and Reputation in the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The aſperſions caſt upon me are either that I am</hi> Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical, an Enemy to the Church, <hi>or that I am</hi> Heretical: <hi>To both which I crave leave to anſwer, and make my juſt defence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That I am Schiſmatical, or a Sectary, I know not why any man ſhould think ſo; it is true that I hold com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with, and obſerve the laws of Piety and holy Charity with that Chriſtian people to whom Mr.</hi> John Goodwin <hi>is Paſtour; and this I alwayes thought I might do with the ſalvage of truth, honour and conſcience; and yet that it might be known that in that congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are perſons of greater wiſdom, moderation and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, then to confine the adminiſtration of Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces within their own precinct;</hi> I <hi>think it not amiſs to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the courteous</hi> Reader, <hi>that with their permiſſion I do perform all thoſe Miniſterial duties that any Church Officer does in the place where he lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If it be the</hi> Epiſcopal <hi>party that cenſures me for ſchiſm,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118624:3"/> 
               <hi>I humbly crave leave to remonſtrate, that I entered the Miniſtry at a time when there was no Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment eſtabliſh't, but every one did that which was right in his own eyes; as I had no hand in pulling down their Hierarchy, ſo will they not (I hope) blame me for join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a people that I thought eſpouſed the intereſt of truth and holineſs, ſince I did it (as appeares by my practice) with the preſervation of that Miniſterial free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and liberty which any Officer Eccleſiaſtical either juſtly exerciſeth, or pretendeth unto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If it be the</hi> Presbyterian <hi>party, if I had made any ſchiſm, of all men they have the leaſt reaſon to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it; He that is of them without ſin in this kind, let him caſt the firſt ſtone at me; (to borrow our Saviour's words.) For if the little Foxes and Boars have entered to root up and deſtroy the vinyard, it was by that ſchiſm or gap which themſelves made, therefore the Brethren of the Presbytery remembring their own faults this day, will (I hope) exerciſe great lenity and grace towards thoſe that are found in the ſame ſinne and tranſgreſſion (if it be a ſin and tranſgreſſion) with themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To both parties (whom I wiſh may be no more cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led two, but one) I ſhall onely add this, That when the fence is made up, which how ſtrong ſoever it may be, I wiſh may not be too ſtrait, I muſt either keep out, or at my further peril. The</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Second part of my accuſation, is Error and Hereſie; Erroneous I may be,</hi> Humanum eſt Errare; <hi>Heretical I cannot be, becauſe never cenſured by any lawful Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: I know not what brought me ſo much as into ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the City, unleſs it were for my Judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the death of Chriſt, Election and Reprobation,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb facs="tcp:118624:4"/> 
               <hi>wherein I am ſure I hold nothing contrary to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of</hi> England <hi>contained in her</hi> 39. <hi>Articles, and interpreted, according to her moſt learned and beſt beloved children, as Dr.</hi> Hamond, <hi>Dr.</hi> Taylor, <hi>Mr.</hi> Thorndike, <hi>Mr.</hi> Thruſcroſs, Mr. Gunning, Mr. Pearce. <hi>Now having ſo often profer'd to the Commiſſioners for Approbation, and others,</hi> bona fide, <hi>to ſubſcribe theſe forementioned Articles, which contain the Doctrine of our reformed Religion ever ſince the time of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there is no ground in the world why any man ſhould accuſe me either for Novelliſm, or Opinion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But becauſe ſome men may even cenſure the Articles themſelves, and becauſe I am extreamly deſirous to cut off all future jealouſies concerning me, touching the five ſo much controverted points, I will here propoſe my ſence in mine own terms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>I.</hi> That God's Eternal Decrees of Election and Reprobation, are not of Qualities, but of Perſons.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>II.</hi> That Grace of God which is afforded unto all men, is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to leave men without excuſe.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>III.</hi> That the death of Chriſt is ſufficient for all; but none ſhall have benefit by him but thoſe that believe.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>IV.</hi> That no man hath power of himſelf to do any thing that good is, but ſtandeth in need of the preventing, exciting, and aſſiſting Grace of God in Chriſt, for the beginning, progreſs, and perſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in all good. <hi>Or thus:</hi> The will of man ſet at liberty by grace, is onely free in its choice both of good and evil.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>V.</hi> That there is a ſtate of grace attainable in this life, from which it is difficult, if not impoſſible to fall away.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:118624:4"/> More particularly I now come to ſatisfie the Chriſtian Reader concerning the following Diſcourſe: The of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence that was taken at my Sermon, was either in groſs from the general tendency of it, or in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, from that diſtinction which I made 'twixt good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Mercy, and from that paſsage concerning the puniſhment of Blaſphemy: To hoth which (good Reader) I ſhall crave the leave both to explain my ſelf, and give my Reaſons.</q>
            <p n="1">1. For the general and natural tendency of my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, I think it was for Peace, Love, Mercy and Unity; and if any thing otherwiſe either hath, or ſhall enſue upon it, it is abſolutely contrary to its primitive intention: I am indeed (till <hi>I</hi> ſee reaſon for the contrary) very much perſwaded of the equity and reaſonableneſs of ſuffering with lenity and moderation, all thoſe that diſſent in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, provided they trample not upon Authoritie, make no breach upon the civil peace, offer no violence or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honor unto thoſe who are different in their perſwaſions from them. Here I take ſhelter under the great St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> who writing to <hi>Proculianus</hi> the Donatiſt, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth, That ſuch as err from the Truth muſt be drawn home by mild inſtruction, and not by cruel enforcement. When Biſhop <hi>Itacius</hi> (as my Author informs me) had
<pb facs="tcp:118624:5"/> put to death <hi>Priſcilian,</hi> and divers of his Followers, <hi>Anno</hi> 383, he was firſt condemned for that bloodie act by <hi>Theogniſtus</hi> and <hi>St. Ambroſe;</hi> afterwards meeting ſome Biſhops at <hi>Triers</hi> that had partaken with <hi>Itacius</hi> in his bloodie execution, refuſed to have any Communion with them: Neither do I think can it be made appear, that the Councils of <hi>Nice, Calcedon,</hi> or <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> made uſe of any other weapons againſt the Arrians, Neſtorians, Macedonians, but the Word of God.</p>
            <p>And my ſame Author brings in <hi>Thuanus proaem. in Hiſto, p.</hi> 5. a Romaniſt challenging all the world to ſhew him any approved euample in all the Monuments of Antiquitie, of any execution done upon the Opinioniſts of thoſe times, but that the Church of God did alwaies ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor the ſhedding of blood, in matters that meerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd Religion. To denie unto men the exerciſe of their Religion, (provided, as before, they keep the civil peace) is that which neither the <hi>Pole,</hi> nor the <hi>French</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie unto the <hi>Hugonets,</hi> the Sectaries of thoſe parts.</p>
            <p>That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould impoſe in matters of Religion, is ſo far rational, that ſhe doth pretend to an high infallibilitie: but why one Miniſter ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon another, one Proteſtant upon another, when neither the one, or the other, does ſo much as pretend to infallibillity, for the preſent I ſee not; and ſhould be
<pb facs="tcp:118624:5"/> glad that any perſon of piety and learning would give me ſober reaſons of Conviction.</p>
            <p>In particular, concerning that diſtinction which I gave <hi>twixt goodneſs and mercie in God;</hi> for which ſome took occaſion boldly to aver, That I denied the Attributes of God: whoever they were, they fulfilled the old ſaying, <hi>Fortiter calumniare, aliquid adhaeretis;</hi> and I hope I ſhall wipe off both the dirt and the ſtain by denying it: I will not diſparage the Auditory at <hi>Pauls</hi> ſo far as to make any other explanation then what I then made, and to which I refer the Reader; as it is truly tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed and printed: for when we ſaid, that God could not be merciful, till the creature, ſin and miſery opened a door thereunto; we ſpake of mercy <hi>in actu exercito,</hi> in the exrciſe and practice thereof; and in this ſenſe onely it ſeemeth diſtinguiſhable from goodneſs, and in all other reſpects identified, and made one with it; for mercy it is elicit, and drawn forth of goodneſs by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of want and miſery.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond and laſt place, That which was moſt excepted againſt, and which hath opened the mouths of ſo many men againſt me, was that one Expreſsion, <hi>That I could ſubſcribe to puniſh Blaſphemy according to the Judaical Law, if there were any perſon to be found who could infallibly</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118624:6"/> 
               <hi>determine it:</hi> This is all that was ſpoken (more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> leſs) upon this Subject; and what grounds there may be for it, thou ſhalt judge.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider, that at that time when this Law was put in execution againſt Blaſphemers, the Jews that were entruſted therewith, were ſuch as had an immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, and conſequently, infallible Direction in all diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult and important Caſes, from God himſelfe, and therefore could not ſwerve in the Adminiſtration of Judgement, unleſs they would directly oppoſe the plain and poſitive Determination of God himſelf; but ſince we cannot expect any ſuch immediate Direction or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination, in an Affair of this importance, whether we ought to put any ſuch Law in execution, ought to be the ſubject of our ſerious thoughts and inquiry.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is worth our conſideration how the Jews made the ordinary and common naming of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> to be blaſphemous, and puniſhable by death, judging it warrantable from the Letter of that Text, <hi>Lev.</hi> 24. 11. <hi>And the Iſraelitiſh Womans Son blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Name of the Lord;</hi> it is in the <hi>Septua.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>And naming the Name of the Lord, curſed:</hi> And Ver. 16. without the explication or addition of <hi>curſing,</hi> or <hi>execration,</hi> its ſaid, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>He that</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118624:6"/> 
               <hi>meth the Name of the Lord, ſhall ſurely be put to death;</hi> though our tranſlation hath it, <hi>He that blaſphemeth the Name of the Lord, ſhal ſurely be put to death.</hi> Now I ſubmit it to the Judgements of the Wiſe, how difficult it is to ſtate the Nature of <hi>Blaſphemy;</hi> how high, or how far the Expreſsion muſt go, to bring the perſon in danger of this Law, and how requiſite it was even for the Elders of the Congregation to put the Offender in Ward, (as they u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to do) till the <hi>mind of God was known concerning this thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Law againſt Blaſphemie ſeemeth to be much of the ſame kind with that (equally ſevere) againſt preſumptuous Sins, <hi>Numb.</hi> 15. 30. <hi>But the ſoul that doth ought preſumptuouſly, whether he be born in the Land, or a Stranger, the ſame reprocheth the Lord, that Soul ſhal ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly be cut off, (i. e.)</hi> Puniſhed with death: An Inſtance is there given, <hi>Ver.</hi> 32. <hi>They found a man that gathered ſticks on the Sabbath-day, and they brought him unto</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Aaron, <hi>and unto all the Congregation, and they put him in Ward, becauſe it was not declared what ſhould be done unto him.</hi> We obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. There was an Atonement to be made for ſins of Ignorance; but ſins of Preſumption were to be puniſhed by Death.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb facs="tcp:118624:7"/> 2. Preſumption, or as ihe <hi>Septuagint</hi> reads it, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to ſin <hi>with an hand of pride,</hi> is ſuch a ſin that cannot be judged of accurately, and diſtinctly, by any ſave God onely; men may gueſs, but it belongs unto God to paſs a definitive Sentence. The man was brought into juſt ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that had gathered ſticks on the Sabbath-day; but how far God would interpret it preſumptuous, neither <hi>Moſes</hi> nor the Congregation could deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine: <hi>Therefore they put him in Ward till they knew the mind of God.</hi> Obſerve <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader,</hi> that the Enquirie which they made at the mouth of God, ſeems not to be concerning the Puniſhment, (for that was determined before, <hi>The ſoul that doth ought preſumptuouſly, ſhall be cut off,)</hi> but concerning the Sin, how far God would interpret it preſumptuous, and within the Cognizance of his own Law: Hence I infer, That if <hi>Moſes</hi> could not judge (as to this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute) in the breach of a known Law, ſuch as was the breaking of the Sabbath by gathering ſticks thereon; of how much greater difficulty is it for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſon or perſons now living, to ſtate and define the whole nature and extent of Blaſphemy? which
<pb facs="tcp:118624:7"/> is neceſſary for the Judges that ſit upon life and deatb.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Beſides, if we will make the Judicial Law bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and ſtill in force for the puniſhment of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendors in Religion in one caſe, why not in all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes? <hi>(i. e.)</hi> of things <hi>in eodem genere,</hi> in the ſame kind; If Blaſphemy, why not Sabbath-breaking, eſpecially ſince we make it <hi>Jure Divino?</hi> Why do we not puniſh <hi>Atheiſm, Idolatry, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſm, Swearing, Execration,</hi> or any preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Sin, with death, according to the rigour of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law? In theſe things I am bold to offer my thoughts, and do with all poſſible humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſubmit my Apprehenſions to be regulated by bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Judgements; hoping, <hi>Chriſtian Reader,</hi> thou wilt take theſe things with the ſame <hi>candor</hi> they are now delivered unto thee; and <hi>the God of Peace</hi> that brought again our Lord Jeſus Chriſt <hi>from the dead, eſtabliſh thee</hi> in the Truth, and preſerve thee in perfect Love and Charity unto the <hi>State and Kingdom</hi> whereinto no <hi>Atheiſt, Idolater, Blaſphemer,</hi> ſhall enter; where the Church ſhall <hi>be no longer Militant,</hi> in diverſity of Opinions, but Triumphant, in <hi>abſolute and entire Love and Unity,</hi> where all Gods People
<pb facs="tcp:118624:8"/> with <hi>one heart, and one mind ſhall join</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the bleſſed <hi>Angels in one Chore; Perpetuas Dei Celebrare laudes, &amp; aeternum cantare</hi> Hallelujah.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>APol. <hi>pag.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>r.</hi> mine: <hi>p.</hi> 2. Marg. <hi>r.</hi> innoxias. <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>r.</hi> equipollent. <hi>p.</hi> 6. <hi>l.</hi> ult. <hi>r.</hi> Meſſiah. <hi>p</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 27. <hi>r.</hi> Officio: <hi>p.</hi> 9. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>r.</hi> fructus. ibid <hi>l.</hi> 20: <hi>r.</hi> Acts. <hi>p.</hi> 14. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>r.</hi> fuco. ibid. <hi>l.</hi> ult. <hi>r.</hi> Agricola. <hi>p</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 11. <hi>r.</hi> Aquinas. <hi>p</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 35. <hi>r.</hi> with. <hi>p.</hi> 13. <hi>l.</hi> 32. <hi>r.</hi> Theſe. <hi>p.</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>r.</hi> aſſimilate. <hi>p.</hi> 23. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>r.</hi> Field. <hi>p</hi> 28. <hi>l.</hi> 14 <hi>r.</hi> ultionum. <hi>p.</hi> 29. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>for</hi> unto that day, <hi>read</hi> unto us in that day. <hi>p.</hi> 30. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>r.</hi> like. ibid. <hi>l.</hi> 11. <hi>r.</hi> genius.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118624:8"/>
            <head>A Pattern of Mercy.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>THE TEXT. Luke 6. 36.</bibl>
               <q>Be ye therefore merciful, as your heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is merciful.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is part of our Saviour's Sermon, either up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or at his coming down from the Mount; and therefore doth highly challenge and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeake our beſt attention and obſervation, ſince it is no ordinary Teacher, but the great Maſter of Truth, the great Doctor of the World that ſpeaketh.</p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of Mercifulneſs, I preſume will ſeem neither <hi>low,</hi> nor yet <hi>unſeaſonable</hi> in this Auditory; not <hi>low,</hi> becauſe the ſubject of our bleſſed Saviour, and directed to his own Diſciples, not excluding the reſt of his Auditors gathered together in great multitudes for to hear him: Not <hi>unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> ſince we dwell in an age wherein thoſe black paſſions of Envy, Jealouſie, Hatred; thoſe ſad diſtempers of Malice, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, Cruelty, are ſo great and predominant.</p>
            <p>The Evangelical Duties that are ſcattered in this Book, are in this reſpect not unlike the <hi>Proverbs</hi> of <hi>Solomon,</hi> that have no great connexion with, or dependance one upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118624:9"/>
            <p> That which relates unto the Text, begins <hi>Verſe</hi> 27. where he urgeth them [to <hi>do good to thoſe that hate them:]</hi> and <hi>ver.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Duplex eſt autem reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendi mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus; alter quo inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xius arae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias; alter quo retali amus.</hi> Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin.</note> 29. [to <hi>him that ſmiteth thee on the one cheek, offer alſo the other:] i. e.</hi> Be far from Revenge; do not oppoſe violence with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; but put up, rather then repay an Injury; <hi>[and him that taketb away thy Cloke, forbid not to take thy Coat alſo:]</hi> which is explained <hi>Matt.</hi> 5. 40. <hi>[if any man will ſue thee at the law,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, go to Law with thee, and take away thy coat, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> If any man go about to rob thee of thy coat by any unjuſt courſe or proceſs at law, rather then oppoſe violence or fraud, to his deceit and injuſtice, let him take thy Cloke al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; not that our Saviour herein forbids Chriſtians to make uſe of the Civil Law for the maintenance of themſelves, their juſt Rights and Properties; for this were to expoſe them (too obnoxious already) to the ravenous appetite of every covetous and unjuſt perſon.</p>
            <p>Verſe 30. <hi>[Give to every man that asketh: (i. e.</hi> ſuch as we judge are in need; the poor are the proper and neceſſary objects of every good mans charity) <hi>and of him that</hi> taketh away thy goods, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(i. e.)</hi> that taketh thy goods upon lone, that borroweth of thee, [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>ask them not again, (i. e.)</hi> Exact them not again by hard Uſury, and oppreſſion; which ſeemeth to be the ſame with that <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. as <hi>mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um exigor debitum, repoſco.</hi>
               </note> 42. <hi>Give to him that asketh, and from him that would borrow of thee, turn not thou away;</hi> In St. <hi>Matthew</hi> we are commanded not to refuſe to lend to thoſe that would borrow; and in St. <hi>Luke,</hi> not to exact what we do lend, with cruelty and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.</p>
            <p>He urgeth them unto this,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Ab aequitate,</hi> from the equity and reaſonableneſs of it. ver. 31. <hi>And as ye would men ſhould do to you, do ye alſo to them likewiſe;</hi> make their caſe your own, and what you would have done to you, were you in their condition, do you the ſame for them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By an Argument drawn, <hi>à minori ad majus,</hi> ver. 34. <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners lend to ſinners, to receive as much again:</hi> If you only have a common and ordinary love and charity for thoſe which have the ſame for you, what reaſon or ground have you to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118624:9"/> expect Divine Remuneration? But as it is ver. 35. <hi>Love your Enemies, and your reward ſhall be great, and ye ſhall be the children of the higheſt, for he is kind unto the unthankful, and the evil;</hi> From whence he infers the duty in the Text, and ſhuts up that part of his Diſcourſe; <hi>Be ye therefore merciful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not ſpend time in opening of the words, (there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing in them but what is obvious to the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Underſtanding) leaſt I ſhould ſeem to raiſe a duſt with my feet, and make the Comment more dark then the Text.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A duty enjoined, <hi>Be ye merciful.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The meaſure or pattern of this duty, <hi>as your heavenly Father.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In both which, we have three things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The mercifulneſs of the Divine being declared, <hi>Your heavenly Father is merciful.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The Creatures mercifulneſs enjoined, <hi>Be ye merciful.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. The aſſimulation likeneſs, and proportion that ought to be 'twixt the one and the other, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>your heavenly father is merciful.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Hence I might lay down three Axioms or Divine Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That God is merciful.</item>
               <item>2. That we ought to be merciful.</item>
               <item>3. That Gods mercifulneſs is the Copy &amp; Rule of ours.</item>
            </list>
            <p>But I will not caſt the words into any other Mould then that wherein they lye in the Text, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That we all ought to be merciful, even as our heavenly Father is merciful.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section__method">
               <head>METHOD.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. I ſhall give you an account what mercy is, and what it imports in the phraſe of the Scripture.</item>
                  <item>2. Wherein the mercifulneſs of our heavenly Fathers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that we may ſee wherein we are to imitate him.</item>
                  <item>3. What reaſons and grounds we have to be merciful as he is merciful.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. Concerning Mercey: Sometimes Mercy is the ſame with Pity, Compaſſion, and Tenderneſs: <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 1. the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118624:10"/> exhorts to Unity by the conſolation of Chriſt, by the comforts of Love, by the fellowſhip of the Spirit, by <hi>bowels</hi> and <hi>mercies, (i. e.)</hi> If there be any tenderneſs, pity and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion in you towards your common Father, <hi>fulfil you my joy;</hi> where <hi>bowels</hi> and <hi>mercies</hi> are equipolent terms, that ſerve to illuſtrate and explain the ſenſe one of another: To this we may refer that of the Prophet, <hi>Jer</hi> 31. 20. where God is brought in troubled and diſcompoſed in himſelf for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment and affliction of <hi>Ephraim; Is Ephraim my dear Son? Is he a pleaſant child? for ſince I spake</hi> againſt him, I do <hi>earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remember him, therefore my</hi> bowels <hi>are troubled for him, I will ſurely have mercy upon him, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Mercy is the ſame with pardon, remiſſion and forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 13. <hi>Who, was before a blasphemer, and a perſecutor, and injurious; but I obtained Mercy, becauſe I did it ignorantly, (i. e.)</hi> being ſo much unfit and unworthy whil'ſt I was a <hi>Jew,</hi> blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming Chriſt, and perſecuting his people; yet I obtained <hi>mercy, (i. e.)</hi> pardon and forgiveneſs of God, God looked upon it as an act of blind zeal in me, and not of propenſe malice againſt them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Mercy is uſed for the donation or vouchſafement of ſome Priviledge ſpiritual or temporal, unto a perſon or peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 10. <hi>Which in times paſt were not a people, but are now the people of God, which had not obtained mercy, but now have obtained mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is ſuppoſed to have been written from <hi>Rome</hi> to the converted Jews, and then the meaning ls this; You that for a long time (for this Epiſtle is believed to have been written <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 44.) whilſt Chriſt was upon the earth had not the happineſs to receive Chriſt and the Goſpel, now are made partakers of this great Mercy and Priviledge, <hi>viz.</hi> to come into the Church and Houſe of God.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 16. <hi>It is not of him that willeth, nor of him that run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, but of God that ſheweth mercy.</hi> The Apoſtle here argueth in the behalf of God, that he was at full liberty in the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and diſtribution of his Mercies, and that he did the Jews no wrong in calling the Gentiles to Chriſtianity, Ver. 15. <hi>As he ſaith unto Moſes, I will have mercy upon whom I will</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118624:10"/> 
                  <hi>have mercy,</hi> &amp;c. As if he had ſaid unto him, In the diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of my bleſſings I will do what I think good, without giving thee or any man a reaſon, though I have alwayes rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for what I do; yet as it is ver. 13. <hi>Jacob have I loved, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau have I hated,</hi> which is either true in the Letter, in chuſing the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and rejecting the <hi>Idumeans;</hi> or elſe in the Type, in preferring the Covenant of Grace before the Covenant of Works; <hi>So then it is not of him, &amp;c. (i e.)</hi> in point of merit, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, or condignity, <hi>but of God that ſheweth mercy; (i. e.)</hi> vouchſafeth to call the Gentiles to Chriſtianity, when the obſtinate and incredulous Jewes have rejected it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Mercy is taken for Charity, or that relief which we give unto the poor, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. 27. <hi>Breake off thy ſins by righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and thine iniquities by ſhewing mercy unto the poor; (i. e.)</hi> by being liberal &amp; charitable towards the poor; in which ſence many underſtand that of <hi>Peter</hi> 1. 4. 8 <hi>Charity covereth a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſins.</hi> So likewiſe it is uſed <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 26. <hi>He is ever merciful, and lendeth, and his ſeed is bleſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the further opening the nature of Mercy, obſerve the difference betwixt Goodneſs and Mercy: Goodneſs in God is ſuppoſed to be abſolute, but Mercy is a relative thing: God might have been good to all Eternity, though man had ſtood, yet Merciful he could not have been without a ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and introduction of ſin.</p>
               <p>As all Pardon includes an offence, ſo all Mercy involves want and miſery: Goodneſs ſuppoſeth a man, Mercy a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Goodneſs ſuppoſeth a man in being; Mercy, a man in miſery: God might have been eternally good, and tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently glorious in the free communication of himſelfe, though ſin and miſery had never introduced mercy.</p>
               <p>Goodneſs and Mercy are thus diſtinguiſhable in men; Goodneſs is the Root, and Mercy the Branch growing out from it; We muſt firſt be good in ourſelves, before we can be merciful towards others: We muſt as our Saviour ſheweth, firſt make the Tree good, before we can bring forth good fruit. Charity begins at home; if we be not good, have not an inward principle of Goodneſs in our ſelves, how can we laudably exerciſe any pity or compaſſion, any bounty or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118624:11"/> clemency, any love or charity towards others.</p>
               <p>So much for the firſt point.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Br.</hi> Come we now to ſpeak of the mercifulneſs of God, and produce a great Copy and Exemplar for your imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And now methinks we are fallen upon the nobleſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in the World, being we are to treat of Divine Mercy, which the Scriptures declare, which men experience, which the Devils envy, the good Angels admire, and which all the World ought to adore.</p>
               <p>A man that looks down from an high Precipice, albeit he is in no danger of falling, yet would his fear ſeize him, and a ſecret trembling take hold of him: The Scriptures and our own experience have ſet us upon a great Mount, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to look down upon the great abyſſe of Divine Mercies, we are ready to cry out with the <hi>Apoſtle, Rom.</hi> 11. 33. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>O the depth of the riches both of the Wiſdom and the mercies of God</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall ſpeak to this, 1. Negatively. 2ly. Poſitively.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In that he beareth with the daily violation of his truth, and ſuffereth with incredible lenity, the breaches that are made upon it, &amp; though men do not believe what God ſaith, nay, (which is more) do believe things different and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thereunto, yet ſtill God containeth himſelf, and doth not with-hold his Mercy from them. The Church of God is ſaid to be <hi>the ground and pillar of truth,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 15. The Church it is that ſacred Depoſitary wherein the truth is laid up. The Frogs of <hi>Aegypt</hi> were not more numerous, that came craw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into the Kings Palace, then the Errors and mis-ſhapen Opinions, which in all Ages (eſpecially in this) have infeſted the Church, the houſe of God; and herein the mercifulneſs of God appears, that he does not preſently rid himſelf of them, nor deſtroy the men for their opinion ſake.</p>
               <p>In the Jewiſh Church he ſuffered the <hi>Eſſens,</hi> (a penſive and melancholy Sect) who ſleighted the Hierarchy of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> diſſented from the common way of Worſhip, and held Community, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> reports of them.</p>
               <p>He ſuffered the Herodians, <hi>Mark</hi> 3. 6. a politick and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious Sect, who thought <hi>Herod</hi> the <hi>Aſchalonite</hi> to bee the <hi>Meſſiahs, the ſent of God:</hi> and thence called Herodians: It
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118624:11"/> is likely they were abuſed into that opinion, from the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtruing the prophecie of <hi>Jacob,</hi> Gen. 49. 10. <hi>That the ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter ſhould not depart from Judah, nor a Law-giver from between his knees, till the Shilo came.</hi> Hence they might conclude that <hi>Herod</hi> was the <hi>Shilo,</hi> becauſe the enſigns of Royalty and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ceaſed from the Aſmonean race, and <hi>Herod</hi> a ſtranger, the ſon of <hi>Antipater,</hi> an Idumean, ſucceeded by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt uſurpation in the Government of Judea.</p>
               <p>He ſuffered the Samaritans, who though they acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the five Books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet denied the Authority of the Prophets, becauſe they judged them not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>inſpired by God;</hi> and likewiſe ſleighted the Temple conſecrated at Jeruſalem, and worſhipped the God of Iſrael upon mount Gerizim. Where firſt they had a magnificent Temple built by <hi>Sanballat</hi> a Samaritane-Prince, in oppoſition to <hi>Jaddus</hi> the High-prieſt of the Jews; and when it was afterward de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroied and razed to the ground by <hi>Hircanus</hi> the Maccabae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, the earth remained ſacred to them on which it ſtood, and continued a place of Worſhip to the daies of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, Joh. 4. 20. <hi>Our fathers worſhipped in this mountain, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He ſuffered the Sadduces, mentioned <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the ſouls immortality, and all future eſtate and being after this life; many of them ſerving God zealouſly and ſtrictly, according to the preſcript of <hi>Moſes</hi> his Law, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on no other expectations then a temporal reward upon earth.</p>
               <p>In the Gentile world the mercifulneſs of God appears, that he does not rain down fire from heaven to avenge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of thoſe Idolaters, who worſhip the Hoſt of Heaven, the Sun, Moon, and Stars which he hath created: And ſtill he beareth with almoſt incredible clemency and mercy in the Chriſtian world, thoſe ſtrange, monſtrous, and abſurd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions that are framed of him, he ſuffereth himſelf to be repreſented as unjuſt, unwiſe, unmerciful, and whatever is unworthy of his eternal Truth and God-head.</p>
               <p>And there are two things that render his Mercy more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and conſpicuous.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118624:12"/> 1. In that he is infallible in his judgement, liable to no miſtake, or miſ-apprehenſion, and conſequently may be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and definitive in his ſentence and determination; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit he knoweth moſt certainly the difference 'twixt good and evil, light and darkneſs, truth and error, yet he build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing thereupon (unleſs in ſome extraordinary caſes) to man's outward prejudice and damage; but endeavoureth by the light ſhining in us, by the inſpirations and notices of his ſpirit, by the convictions and authority of his word, to reduce humane conceptions to a likeneſs with, and confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity unto the fair and beautiful Idea's ſet up in his own mind, and declared unto us in his holy Word of Truth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In that he is of Power ſufficient to vindicate the ſacred honour and credit of his Truth, and to avenge himſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Erroniſts, the Tranſgreſſors thereof; He hath the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of life and death, health and ſickneſs, poverty and plenty; and were he ſo minded, he needs not be beholden to any arm or power to aſſiſt him.</p>
               <p>If it were objected, <hi>God puniſheth not Murder, Theft, &amp;c. it doth not follow that therefore we ſhould not.</hi> To this I anſwer, The caſe is not the ſame; all men have a perfect and diſtinct knowledge what Murder is, what Theft is; but in matters of Opinion concerning Religion and the things of God, there is the greateſt variety and diſcrepancy imaginable; and <note n="*" place="margin">The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> excepted.</note> no man does ſo much as pretend, or lay claim to an unerrancy or infallibility of Judgement: Beſides it is agreed, that the civil Magiſtrate does <hi>ex Offlcio,</hi> puniſh the breach and viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Laws of Nature, and the Laws of God, where he is authorized and appointed ſo to do, let it be ſhown pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitively, that under the Goſpel he ought either <hi>ex officio, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepto, vel exemplo,</hi> to judge, determine, and cenſure opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons abſtracted, and wholly remote from ſecular conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; or let it be ſhewn wherein, or when the People did chuſe them either for their Repreſentatives in Religion; or make them Judges in matters of Opinion and Conſcience, and the Controverſie will preſently ceaſe, and the Diſpute end.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118624:12"/> 2. The mercifulneſs of God appears, in that he ſuffereth the breach and tranſgreſſion of his Laws, and does not ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily avenge himſelf of the tranſgreſſors.</p>
               <p>He looketh into our houſes, and there he findeth profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſenſuality, riot, exceſs.</p>
               <p>He looketh into Chambers, and more ſecret retirements, and behold, wantonneſs, intemperance, luxury, uncleanneſs.</p>
               <p>He looketh into our places of commerce, and there he findeth deceit, fraud, cozenage.</p>
               <p>He looketh into our places of Judicature, and behold, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, partiality, injuſtice, oppreſſion; Or, as it is <hi>Amos</hi> 6. 12. <hi>in cicutam mutatur jus &amp; fractus Justitiaein abſynthium;</hi> Judgment turned into Gall, and the fruit of Righteouſneſs into Worm wood.</p>
               <p>He looketh into our Churches and places of Worſhip, and for Knowledge, he findeth Zeal; for Piety, Intereſt; and for Devotion, little elſe but Curioſity; <hi>ſpectatum veniunt.</hi> Our Churches are turned into Theatres, whereinto we come to ſee, and to be ſeen; not remembring that great Theatre wherein we muſt all appear before the Judgement-Seat of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>In our hearts he beholdeth envy, jealouſie, emulation, cruelty; in our lives diſorders and confuſions, and yet God holdeth his hand, he endeavoureth the reformation, not the deſtructionof of his creatures.</p>
               <p>So great was the mercy of God, that <hi>David</hi> ſeems to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken him, and ſtirred him up to Judgement, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 126. <hi>It is time for thee, O Lord, to work, for they have made void thy Law.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> is forced to make an Apology for God, to the profane ſcoffers, why he ſeemed to defer his coming, and neglect Judgement in taking vengeance upon the World, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 9. <hi>The Lord is not ſlack concerning his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, as ſome men count ſlackneſs, but is long-ſuffering to us ward, not willing that any ſhould periſh; (i. e.)</hi> God does not forget his promiſe, neither is he unmindful of Judgement, but he is loath to come in upon the World at unawares, as a Thief in the night, to overtake them in the height of their preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſecurity, and therefore he extends and lengthens
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118624:13"/> out the day of Grace, that none might periſh, (if't were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) but that all might come to repentance.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We come to ſpeak poſitively.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Mercy it is the ſame with Pity, and in this ſence God is merciful; he is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>full of bowels,</hi> pitiful and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate towards the children of men; he is called, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Pater miſerationum,</hi> the Father of Compaſſions: <note place="margin">Numerus pluralis eſt emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</note> There dwells no hatred, no malice with God; no rancour, exaſperation or cruelty is lodged in his eternal breaſt; he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved man in the ſtate of his innocency, uprightneſs and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and when man degenerated, he turned his love into pity, and his delight into commiſeration; and even then when his Juſtice makes him ſevere, it is exerciſed (to ſpeak after the manner of men) with reluctancy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret.</p>
               <p>The pity and compaſſion which we ſo much admire in men, are but weak umbrages and repreſentations of Gods; and yet the firſt wants not its due praiſe and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>The Court of <hi>Areopagite,</hi> mentioned <hi>Asts</hi> 17. ſo much famed in the World, put to death a young child for that he took an unnatural pleaſure in depriving the very Birds of their ſight, and letting them flye for his recreation; fearing leaſt he who exerciſed ſo timely an apprentiſhip of Cruelty upon Birds, might in his more ripe years exerciſe it upon men.</p>
               <p>The like is reported of the Senate at <hi>Carthage,</hi> who cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured one of their own Citizens for no other cauſe in the world, but that he had civilized and made tractable a Lyon, ſuppoſing ſo frequent a converſation with wild Beaſts, had made him put off all humanity and pity, and degenerate into the nature of that Beaſt with whom he had ſo much converſation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marcellus</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Conſul, being commanded by his Maſters at <hi>Rome</hi> to raze <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> even then when he ſaw their Commands put into execution, and beheld the great City on fire, he began to relent, and (out of his good nature) to ſhed tears in abundance, wherewith if it had been
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118624:13"/> poſſible, he would have quenched thoſe flames which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had kindled.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Caeſar Titus</hi> (whom for his clemency they called the <hi>delight of mankind)</hi> beholding the ſtreets of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with the dead bodies of the Jews, found his heart much touched; but when he ſaw the glorious Temple all on fire, and the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves that were entered thereinto, would not ſuffer it to be quenched, he could then contain himſelf no longer, but with hands to Heaven proteſted that it was the act of the gods, and not effect of his diſpoſition.</p>
               <p>But as the heavens are high above the earth, even ſo are the compaſsions of men exceeded by the compaſsions of God; behold a greater then <hi>Marcellus,</hi> a greater then <hi>Caeſar Titus</hi> is here. Sin hath ſet the world on fire, and we like the Jews, will not ſuffer it to be quenched.</p>
               <p>God came down from heaven in his own perſon, commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated his thoughts to the Patriarchs before and after the Flood, beſeeched his people by his Prophets, and laſtly by his own Son, the man Chriſt Jeſus, and ſtill endeavoureth by his Word and Spirit to quench this great flame and confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration kindled by ſin; ſo that if it be not quenched, but proceed to devour the ſouls of men, God Almighty may with <hi>Caeſar Titus,</hi> enter his juſt proteſtation, that the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the World is an <hi>effect of our Wickedneſs,</hi> and not of his <hi>own inclination and diſpoſition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The love of our gracious God is more to be judged of by what he would do for us, then by what he does for us, though (to ſpeak the truth) he hath done all that did become a great Wiſdom (checked with Juſtice) to do.</p>
               <p>Even as the love of a tender-hearted Father is more ſeen by what he would do for his obſtinate and ungracious Son, (were he a capable ſubject) then by what he ever actually does for him.</p>
               <p>He frowns upon him, gives him correction, diſ-inherits him, and goes down into the grave with a reſolution of not doing him the leaſt good thing for him, (in the ſence the World calls good) and yet whilſt he lived his heart was ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, his bowels yern towards him, his deſires are great
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118624:14"/> that he might enrich him, and his complaints many, that he was not a ſubiect capable of his favour.</p>
               <p>In like manner the love of our heavenly Father is rather to be eſtimated by what he would do for us, then what he does for us, were we capable ſubiects of his Grace and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, according to that, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 29. <hi>O that there were an heart in them, that they would fear me, that it might be well with them and their children for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Soveraign Creator he hates not any thing in the World, becauſe the whole World is the rare and ſingular Workmanſhip of his hands; for as his Wiſdom is free from Error, ſo are his Works devoid of repentance; all things are eminently in him, and under the covert of his pure and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Omnia u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſunt in Deo, &amp; cum Deo, &amp;c.</hi> Ber. Scrm.</note> Eſſence, are hid all creature-perfections whatſoever; <hi>Nec aliunde Justus, aut Bonus, quam unde Magnus;</hi> that I may borrow the expreſsion of that contemplative and devout perſon, which is Engliſh't thus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>That form of Divinity which makes him Great, makes him by the ſame means, Wiſe, Juſt and Good;</hi> which is the true reaſon that he can no more hate or neglect any thing that he hath made, then the Architect or Maſter-builder can ſleight his own piece which he findes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the fair <hi>Idea's</hi> of Art ſet up in his own mind.</p>
               <p>God having thus united all in himſelf, therefore he loves all, and regardeth all, as raies of his own light, iſſues of his own bounty, productions of his own Wiſdom and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; the venom and malignity of the Toad and Aſpick, the poyſon of the Scorpion, which are ſo deſtructive to ours, are very good and ſuitable to their natures; that which is to us poyſon, is to them blood and ſpirits; the giving it to us, and the taking it away from them, we find equally preiudicial to both their natures and ours: May I ſhut up this point in the words of a learned man? <hi>God hates nothing, nor curſeth any thing but what he is not, and he is all, ſin excepted:</hi> It is that alone which he abhorreth, which he accounts worthy of all dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, which he chaſtiſeth here, and which he purſueth with an armed hand to the Gates of hell, and beyond the Gates of hell, and which he will never forgive in its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſubject, either in this world, or in the world to come.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118624:14"/> 2. Take Mercy for Pardon, and in this ſence God is merciful, he is known by this great Title which he aſſumed in that Solemn Publication, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 7. <hi>Keeping Mercy for thouſands, forgiving Iniquity, Tranſgreſſion and Sin.</hi> It is the glory of a man, much more of God to paſs by an offence; God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deſire ſin, (as no man can wiſh to be diſpleaſed) but man having ſinned, it is infinitely pleaſing to the Divine Nature to ſhew mercy, pardon and forgiveneſs: He that hath ſet us that Rule, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 22. That we ſhould not onely forgive till <hi>ſeven times,</hi> but until <hi>ſeventy times ſeven,</hi> wil not tranſgreſs it himſelf.</p>
               <p>God excepts againſt no mans perſon, but as it is <hi>Prov.</hi> 28. 13. <hi>Whoſoever confeſſeth his ſins, and forſaketh them, ſhall have mercy.</hi> Becauſe God reſpecteth no mans perſon, therefore he excepteth againſt no mans perſon: As he hath <hi>no mans per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in admiration becauſe of advantage,</hi> ſo he hath no mans per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in diſdain becauſe of preiudice.</p>
               <p>As there is no perſon excepted from the general pardon of the Goſpel, upon the terms propoſed therein; ſo is there no ſin excepted, ſave onely that ſin unto death, the nature of which may conſiſt either in the contempt or deſpair of the pardon it ſelf: The mercy of heaven ſhineth forth in this, that God is pleaſed to take our ſubmiſsions, accept of our acknowledgements, and admit us to repentance; <hi>Eſau found no place for repentance, though he ſought it with tears, Heb.</hi> 12. 17. <hi>(i. e.)</hi> He found no place for repentance with his Father <hi>Iſaac;</hi> for as it is in the ſame verſe, <hi>how that afterward when he would have inherited the bleſſing he was rejected;</hi> poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting unto the ſtory <hi>Gen.</hi> 27. <hi>But with God is mercy, and with him is plenteous redemption.</hi> True indeed, God pardons no mans ſins before they be repented of; there are no indulgencies grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in heaven, and obtained on earth by unrepentant ſinners.</p>
               <p>To ſay that ſome mens ſins are pardoned before they be committed; or that they are pardoned paſt, preſent and to com; or which is all one, that they are pardoned from eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is queſtionleſs a Doctrine (to borrow the expreſsion of a learned man) that tranſcends the licentiouſneſs of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and is of worſe conſequence then the <hi>Roman</hi> Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118624:15"/> and were there another <hi>Luther</hi> now alive, he would enter his diſſent from this Doctrine, and make it another ground of ſeparation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If you take Mercy for the vouchſafement of grace and favour unto a perſon or people, and in this ſence God is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, having called all the World unto peace and felicities by the Goſpel; the Scriptures declare it, Experience ſo far as it extendeth, confirmeth it, all Reaſon and Authority e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſheth it, 1 <hi>Col.</hi> 23. <hi>If you continue in the Faith, &amp;c. not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved away from the hope of the Goſpel which ye have heard, &amp; which was preached to every creature which is under heaven; (i. e.)</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Jews, but alſo to the Gentiles; it is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>in every creature;</hi> which intimates not onely the vocal and external, but alſo the internal and ſpiritual preaching of it. In this Goſpel we are told of the blood of ſprinkling <hi>that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth better things then that of Abel: Abel</hi> died in former time, and his blood cryed Juſtice; Chriſt dyed in the fulneſſe of time, and his blood cryed Mercy: We are told of a potent Advocate that continually intercedeth for us in Heavens Court; We hear of the full and moſt gracious promiſes that Almighty God can make to all burdened and heavy laden ſouls, and that whoſoever comes unto him in the Name of Chriſt, he <hi>will in no wiſe caſt out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And all this is laid down in a moſt plain and intelligible way, <hi>ſine fraude &amp; fuce,</hi> without any ſecret Will, any double mind, or mental reſervation; God hath waſhed his hands in innocency, and is free from the death of all men; the dſteru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of men is of themſelves, and the blood of ſouls upon their own heads.</p>
               <p>A queſtion might here be moved, How the mercifulneſs of God is conſiſtent with his Severity; we all underſtand how Mercy is conſiſtent with Juſtice; but how Mercy and Severity ſtand together, is the ſubject of our preſent Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and diſquiſition. We find the Apoſtle puts Goodneſs and Severity together, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11 22 <hi>Behold therefore the goodneſs and ſeverity of God,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>on them which fell, ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but towards thee, goodneſs;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Severity comes from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Metaphor taken <hi>ab arte Agricola,</hi> from the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118624:15"/> off unprofitable branches, and ſo made applicable up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion, unto God, who cuts off unprofitable members both in Church and State. In the ſolution of this queſtion,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. I ſhall give you ſeveral inſtances of Divine Severity.</item>
                  <item>2. I ſhall by a common diſtinction make peace betwixt the one and the other, ſetting God's Severity and Mercy at a good conſiſtency together.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Inſtances are many.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Of the fallen Angels, when all was peace in Heaven, and a bleſſed ſecurity inviron'd them, a thought of Pride did but ſpring up in them, <hi>(Aquinus</hi> thinks it was no more) and God changed countenance preſently, tumbled them out of Heaven, and as the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks <hi>Cap. &amp; v.</hi> 6. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>he hath reſerved them in everlaſting Chains, unto the Judgement of the great Day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. After that God had made unto himſelf another friend of fleſh and blood, placed him in Paradice, converſed with him moſt familiarly, made him his Subſtitute, Vice-gerent and Deputy here on earth, imparted unto him not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the reſt of the creatures, but his image, likeneſs and ſimilitude, provided him an Aſſociate and Companion that might bear him company in this his abode on earth; and yet behold the Severity of God, he committed but one ſin, and that of no great importanee neither, as might ſeem to an eye of fleſh and blood, the eating of an Apple, the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of the forbidden fruit, and that not of his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivement and malice, but at the ſolicitation and importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of another, and yet we ſee what enſued upon this tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſs, the amity and friendſhip 'twixt Heaven and Earth was broken, mans communion with God was interrupted, and he thruſt out of Paradiſe, and condemned to perpetual mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and exile, with his poſterity.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Lots</hi> Wife did but look back from behind her, <hi>in ſtatuam mutatur,</hi> ſhe was turned into a pillar of Salt, and ſo ſhe ſtood for many years, as a monument both of ſeverity and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, till Time (that conſumes all things) removed her, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. 26.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:118624:16"/> 4. <hi>Uzziah</hi> with a good intent laid hold of the Ark, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. 6 to keep it from falling when the Oxen ſhook it, and becauſe his hands were common, and unconſecrated, God there ſmote him, and he dyed by the Ark of God.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A poor man was but gathering a few ſticks on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day; and God commanded him to be ſtoned, <hi>Numbers</hi> 15. 36.</p>
               <p>In the New-Teſtament, <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphyra</hi> did but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire together to tell a lye, and it coſt them both their lives, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Corinthians,</hi> men ſubject to the like paſſions and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities that we are, behaved themſelves irreverently at the Lords Table, and the Text tells us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 30. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>for this very cauſe</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. <hi>many are weak and ſickly among you, and many ſleep.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding all this, the Mercy of God is very well conſiſtent with his Severity, if we conſider a threefold ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of Severity.</p>
               <p>Severity is either in temper and diſpoſition, in purpoſe and decree, or in act and execution.</p>
               <p>In the firſt acceptation, Mercy and Severity are abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inconſiſtent; he that is ſevere in his temper and diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, cannot be likewiſe tender, compaſsionate and merciful in his diſpoſition; theſe two are as contrary and imcompati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as light and darkneſs, cold and heat, that do mutually expel one another: In this ſence God is not ſevere, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> in his temper and diſpoſition.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If we take ſeverity in the decree or purpoſe, ſo it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of an eaſie compliance, and very good conſiſtency with the clemency, long-ſuffering, and mercifulneſs of God.</p>
               <p>A Judge that is merciful in his own nature and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, may yet be very ſtrict and rigid in his decree and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to puniſh offenders, whom no mercy or clemency can obljge, no goodneſs or bounty win upon, or gain.</p>
               <p>In like manner it is which God, of whom we may ſay as <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> ſaies of <hi>Trajan, Eſt piger ad paenas princepi, ad praemia velox,</hi> Slow to puniſh, ſwift to reward; and yet notwithſtanding, he hath formed in himſelf an immutable reſolution &amp; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118624:16"/> (at the regular importunity of his Wiſdom and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice) of puniſhing with rigour and ſeverity all thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially, whom his clemency and mercy could not ſweeten and mollifie: If man will not return, <hi>He hath whet his ſword, and bent his bow, and prepared for him the inſtruments of death,</hi> Pſal. 7. 12.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Severity in the Act or Execution, which is the third acceptation, as in the many inſtances before alledged; which though at the firſt it might ſeem moſt oppoſite and repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to his clemency and mercifulneſs, yet even thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry acts of ſeverity may admit of a gracious conſtruction, if we conſider theſe two things:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That many of thoſe perſons of whom the Scriptures ſpeak, had drunk deep of the cup of divine goodneſs; had been made to reſt under the ſweeteſt influences of his love and favour; and from whom God might have expected bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things. The Angells ſinned whilſt they were before the throne, and in the immediate and actual injoyment of God himſelf. Our firſt parents in Paradice, whilſt they injoied all the felicities heaven and earth could afford them. <hi>Lots</hi> wife againſt the miracle of her deliverance; there was ſomething or other found in them to vindicate that paſſage, <hi>Clementia laeſa vertitur in furorem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. God is ſevere towards one, that he might be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to many; he ſtrikes ſome, that others may take warning? if now and then an act of juſtice and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity was not interpoſed in the world, ſin would grow bold, even to controul the Laws of heaven: God, that he might put a ſtop to the courſe of ſin, gives ample te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of his diſpleaſure againſt it. Like the skilful Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion, that cuts off the gangren'd member, <hi>ne pars ſincera trahatur,</hi> leſt the ſound part ſhould be corrupted.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Br.</hi> Why we ought to be merciful, <hi>as our heavenly father is merciful.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Propter ſimilitudinem,</hi> that wee may bee like unto God.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Propter gratitudinem,</hi> that we may be thankful unto God.</item>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:118624:17"/>
                  <item> 3. <hi>Propter neceſſitatem</hi> (i. e.) <hi>diſpoſitionis &amp; preparationis;</hi> that we may be fit to receive mercy from God.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Propter ſimilitudinem,</hi> that we may be like unto God; which is the Argument in the text, the motive our Saviour uſeth to preſs the duty in hand: There is ſomething in this perſwaſive argument and motive; becauſe it is God's way, it is Chriſt's way, it is the Apoſtles way to preſs unto duty. When God urgeth men unto holineſs, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19. 2. it is by ſomthing of this nature and tenour; <hi>Ye ſhall be holy, for I, the Lord your God, am holy.</hi> When Chriſt preſſeth men to perfection, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 48. ſtill the argunent is drawn from ſimilitude; <hi>Be ye perfect,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, quemadmodum, even as <hi>your heavenly father is perfect.</hi> When St. <hi>John</hi> urgeth Chriſtians unto love, it is drawn from the ſame topick of likeneſs and quality; 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 16. <hi>God is love, and he that dwelleth in love, dwelleth in God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A forcible motive, a cogent argument to prevail with ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional creatures, whether Angels, or men; becauſe of thoſe ſparks of deſires kindled in them, of becoming like unto God; which is not ſimply unlawful, but rather commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable in them.</p>
               <p>We read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14. 12, 15. <hi>How art thou fallen from heaven, O Lucifer, ſon of the morning, &amp;c. for thou hast ſaid in thine heart, I will aſcend into heaven, &amp;c. I will aſcend above the heights of the clouds; I will be like the moſt High: :</hi> which though it be the Prophets triumphant inſultation over Babylon, yet was it true originally of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> The argument was urged by the Serpent, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 4. to perſwade our firſt parents to eat of the forbidden fruit: <hi>[And ye ſhall be as Gods]</hi> a plauſible ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument indeed, to prevail with mortal minds, naturally prone of themſelves to aſpire after likeneſs and ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</p>
               <p>The preſidents I now alledge and ſet before you, to ſhew the force of this argument, and what grounds there are of its ſucceſs and prevalency upon us. Can there be a better reaſon why we ſhould be tender-hearted, merciful, compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate, herein we ſhall be like unto God, we ſhall tranſcend in a manner the line of our Creation, be lifted up above the region of common mortality, and placed in a vicinity and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118624:17"/> ſimilitude of God himſelf. I paſs this, with re-minding you, that as there are ſomethings wherein we are to imitate God, and aſpire after likeneſs unto him, ſo there are other things wherein we are forbid under the penalty of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, ſo much as to aſpire and aſſimulate.</p>
               <p>The ſubject without offence here on earth, may attempt to be like unto his Prince in wiſdom, goodneſs, clemency, patience; but he cannot without rebellion and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence indeavour to be like him in power, greatneſs, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty; we may imitate our Saviours virtues, but not his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles: In like manner we may with ſafety and honour at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt by an holy ambition, to be wiſe, juſt, merciful, <hi>ad exemplar,</hi> according to the original copy, God himſelf, not aſpiring after his greatneſs, power, and majeſty, leſt with <hi>Lucifer,</hi> we incur his hatred and great diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We are to be merciful, <hi>propter gratitudinem,</hi> that we may be thankful unto God; we ſhould ſhew mercy unto others, becauſe our heavenly Father hath ſhown mercy unto us; the very Laws of Gratitude and Retaliation require it: The Reaſon is lodged here, That if God hath forgiven us ten thouſand Talents, ought we not to forgive one another an hundred pence, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 25. The King that did remit ten thouſand Talents, tooke it ill at the hands of his Debtor, that went forth preſently, took his Brother by the Throat that ought him an hundred pence, would not be intreated, but caſt him into priſon till he made him ſatisfaction; Ver. 31. <hi>So when his fellow-ſervants ſaw what was done, they were very ſorry, and came and told unto their Lord all that was done; Ver.</hi> 32. <hi>Then his Lord ſaid, O thou wieked ſervant, I forgave thee all that Debt becauſe thou deſiredſt me, ſhouldſt thou not alſo have had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on thy fellow-ſervant?</hi> Shouldſt thou not? <hi>(i. e.)</hi> thou ſhouldſt have had compaſſion in point of gratitude and thankfulneſs unto me.</p>
               <p>The King in the Parable is God Almighty; the ſervants with whom he reckoneth, are the ſons of men; for we are all the Debtors of Heaven; God for Chriſts ſake doth forgive us many talents: The wicked ſervant is he that takes his Brother by the throat without all mercy and pity, &amp; wil not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118624:18"/> forgive thoſe few pence that his brother oweth him; the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants being <hi>ſorrowful,</hi> ſhews how much it troubles good men to ſee their fellow-creatures ſo hardly dealt with; the <hi>Kings anger</hi> expreſſeth the wrath of God kindled againſt thoſe who are found guilty of this great cruelty and ingratitude; <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty</hi> againſt their Brethren, <hi>ingratitude</hi> againſt their Father; that when God hath forgiven unto them ten thouſand Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, they will not for Chriſts ſake forgive unto their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren an hundred pence.</p>
               <p>God draws us with the Cords of a man, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> with ſuch reaſons and arguments as are proper to work upon the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional nature; to be drawn unto our duty by that ſoft, yet ſtrong cord of Love and Gratitude, is moſt acceptable to God, moſt delightful and pleaſing to our ſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We are to be merciful <hi>propter neceſſitatem,</hi> becauſe of the neceſſity of the thing; if we ſhew not mercy unto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, neither will our heavenly Father ſhew mercy unto us. In the cloſe of that Parable which we quoted before, <hi>Matt.</hi> 18. we read at the 35. <hi>ver. So likewiſe ſhall my heavenly Father do alſo unto you, if ye from your hearts forgive not every one his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their treſpaſſes;</hi> which refers unto the 34. verſe, wherein is expreſſed the rigour and ſeverity of God againſt offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors in this kind, <hi>And his Lord was wrath, and delivered him to the tormentors till he ſhould pay all that was due to him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Saviour likewiſe in that Prayer which bears his Name, teacheth us to pray, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 12. <hi>And forgive us our debts, as we forgive our debters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As it was ſaid by Jeſus Chriſt, That he could do no migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Works becauſe of their unbelief, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 58. meaning, that though he had never ſo great a mind to confirm his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine by Miracles, and to give proof of his being the Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah, yet ſuch was the incredulity and diſtruſt of the <hi>Jews,</hi> his own Countrey-men, that they bound his hands, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him from doing of it.</p>
               <p>Even ſo God Almighty, our gracious and loving Father, though he had never ſo great a mind (to ſpeak after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men) to make us Veſſels of his mercy; yet finding us
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118624:18"/> fraught with all malice and envy, ſtraitened in our bowels, filled with all cruelty, hatred, revenge, we do ſhut up his bounty againſt us, and indiſpoſe him to Mercy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matthew</hi> 57. <hi>Bleſſed are the merciful, for they ſhall obtain mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the merciful ſhall be mercifully dealt with.</p>
               <p>Though our mercifulneſs be not <hi>cauſa propter quam,</hi> the cauſe for which we receive mercy, by way of merit or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity; yet may we ſay it is <hi>cauſa, ſine qua non;</hi> the cauſe, without which we cannot obtain mercy; though not by way of merit or condignity; yet by way of preparation, and Gods gracious diſpoſition.</p>
               <p>Many more grounds and reaſons might be added, but theſe may ſuffice to confirm and eſtabliſh the point in hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section__application">
               <head>Application.</head>
               <p>I ſhall endeavour to improve this Doctrine two wayes.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. By way of imitation.</item>
                  <item>2. By way of conſolation.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. By way of Imitation; Here is an excellent Copy for us to write after; we have ſeen wherein the mercifulneſs of God conſiſts, let us <hi>patrizare,</hi> endeavour to be like unto him.</p>
               <p n="1">1. God beareth with the violation of his truth, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth with incredible patience thoſe erring and wandering ſouls that go aſtray from it; he does not here deſtroy men for their opinions ſake: We dwell in an age wherein we have a large ſubject to exerciſe our clemency, moderation, loving kindneſs, and brotherly forbearance upon. As we ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſo now again, the frogs of <hi>Aegypt</hi> were not more nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous then the errors and miſ-ſhapen opinions that do infeſt the Church of God, and are come up into the Palace of the great King; God ſuffers them, certainly we muſt; if otherwiſe, he would either do it himſelf, or have appointed ſome perſons under the Goſpel to have done it. If <hi>Moſes</hi> was faithful in all things appertaining to the Houſe of God, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt much more; but our great Lord and Maſter, the great Propognour of Truth, directs to no other Weapons to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118624:19"/> to be made uſe of in this Warfare, but ſuch as are ſpiritual; if <hi>his Kingdom</hi> was not of this World, then <hi>muſt not his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants fight:</hi> The Weapon which he hath put into our hands, is his Word, which is <hi>ſharper then any two-edged ſword,</hi> by which we may beſt cut in pieces all thoſe ſnares of error where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Satan hath entangled the ſouls of men.</p>
               <p>When any fall mad, or are diſtracted, bereft of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, though they do or ſay never ſo much evil, though they ſhould blaſpheme God and the King, we are ſo far from cenſuring, puniſhing, or deſtroying them, that we pity them, bewail and lament them, we provide for their cure by all rational means, if haply we may effect their recovery.</p>
               <p>The caſe is much the ſame, (though I do not deſire the parallel ſhould run on four) we cry out againſt Errors, and declaim much againſt thoſe phanatick Opinions that have ſo much troubled Iſrael, and diſturbed the peace of Gods holy Church; and if it were in our power, out of a pang of zeal in killing the Opinioniſts, we might perſwade our ſelves we ſhould do God good ſervice.</p>
               <p>That we do reprove them from the Word of God, that we ſharply cenſure them, that we do warn men both pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely and privately, to take heed to their feet, leſt they be taken in the ſnare of death, and ſo led away with the error of the wicked, is a thing (without queſtion) highly accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God, very uſeful and profitable unto men; and herein the Goſpel from place to place, is our clear rule.</p>
               <p>But that we ſhould touch them in their Eſtates, or practiſe upon their bodies for the cure of their minds; or that we ſhould ſeek to convince them by any other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments then thoſe that are Divine and rational; or where we fall ſhort of conviction, to add force and violence, is a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for the cure of Error, I am not for the preſent perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the great Phyſician of ſouls, Jeſus Chriſt, ever preſcribed. Alas! theſe are poore deluded ſouls, not onely phanatick, but lunatick; how many amongſt us are even diſtracted and bereft of their ſpiritual ſenſes and underſtanding: We are even to bear with them as we do with mad men and children; to take little or no offence at their words, but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118624:19"/> that we be, as the bleſſed Apoſtle would have <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 <hi>Ep. Gap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 25. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in Meekneſs inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. We are to do this from the Divine Precept <hi>Matt.</hi> 13. in the Parable of the tares, Ver. 27. <hi>The ſervants of the houſhold came, and ſaid unto him, Sir, didſt thou not ſow good ſeed in thy Field? from whence then hath it tares?</hi> Ver. 28. <hi>He ſaid unto them, An Enemy hath done this. The ſervants ſaid, Wilt thou then that we go and gather them up.</hi> Ver. 29. <hi>But he ſaid, Nay, leaſt whilſt ye gather up the tares, ye root up alſo the wheat with them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Parable is explained by Chriſt himſelf, 38 <hi>verſ.</hi> The ſeed is the world wherein we all live: obſerve, it is not the Church, but the World; they may be cenſured <hi>in Eccleſia,</hi> in that ſpiritual Court, but not in the World: <hi>[The good ſeed]</hi> are the Children of Truth; or as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Kingdom. The tares are the ſons of Error, the children of the wicked one.</hi> The enemy that ſowed them is the Divel, and thoſe his Emiſſaries whom he imploies. God refers the burning of the Tares till the Harveſt; which our Saviour interprets, the end of the world: and the reaſon why the Tares muſt not be plucked out, but let alone until the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, is this, rendered by himſelf, <hi>ver.</hi> 29. <hi>Leaſt while ye ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up the Tares, ye root up the wheat alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the Tares here can be meant nothing more properly then erroneous perſons: no other ſinners or offenders, but ſinners injudgment, offenders in opinion: For if by Tares we ſhould underſtand Murtherers, Adulterers, Thievs, or any ſuch kind of tranſgreſſors, then would our Saviour be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to plead for a toleration of ſuch ſinners, as his Father had expreſly injoined to be puniſhed: <hi>He that ſheds man's blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed:</hi> He <hi>that ſtole,</hi> to <hi>make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and ſatisfaction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this we may refer the counſel of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> a great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilian, and though not endowed with an infallible ſpirit, yet one as we may preſume, in a ſpecial manner moved by the Spirit, to interpoſe in the behalf of Chriſt and his dear ſervants, to reſcue them from the bloody rage and malice of the Council.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:118624:20"/>
               <p> The Apoſtles ſtanding before the Council, the Jewiſh Presbytery indeavoring to ſuppreſs their erroneous opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for ſo the doctrine of Chriſtianity was accounted, <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliel</hi> ſtands up, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 38. <hi>And now I ſay unto you,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Stand off from thoſe men,</hi> meddle not with them, <hi>let them alone!</hi> for if this counſel, or this work be of men, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> if it be a fancy, or an opinion of their own; if it be of humane invention and contrivance, <hi>it will come to nought,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it will be diſ-jointed, broken, it will ſuffer a diſſolution; <hi>But if it be of God, ye cannot overthrow it; (i. e.)</hi> it will ſtand all oppoſition to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and yee your ſelves bee found fighters againſt God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2ly.</hi> We are urged unto this duty by <hi>example;</hi> and that by the greateſt example, even that of Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4. 55. in the ſtory we have three things conſiderable:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The churliſh in hoſpitality of the Samaritanes, refuſing to give entertainment, not ſo much as a nights lodging unto Chriſt and his Diſciples: and the ground of this was their difference in opinion, as we collect from the 53. <hi>[And they did not receive him, becauſe his face was as though he would go to Jeruſalem;</hi> becauſe he worſhipped not in the ſame place with them, upon Mount <hi>Girizim,</hi> but ſeemed to hold communion with the Jewes in their Worſhip at the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they would not ſo much as receive him into their Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage.</p>
               <p n="2">2. You have the fiery indignation of his Diſciples that was kindled againſt the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> ver. 54. <hi>Wilt thou that we command fire to come down from Heaven, and conſume them, as E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias did?</hi> Here we have a notorious preſident, how far the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate and untutor'd zeal even of good men, may tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port them; it's ſtrange that nothing but fire from heaven can expiate the fault of the Samaritans incivility.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We have our Saviours rebuke and diſcommendation of that raſh zeal wherewith his Diſciples were heated, V. 55. <hi>But he turned and rebuked them,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> he angerly or ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rebuked them, <hi>Ye know not what manner of ſpirit ye are of; i. e.</hi> The Spirit of Chriſt and the Goſpel is another manner
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118624:20"/> of ſpirit then that of the Law, another manner of ſpirit then that of the World: Beſides, its contrary to the end of my coming, that any man ſhould be thus dealt with for any injury or affront done unto me; <hi>The Son of man is not come into the world to destroy mens lives, but to ſave them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To come home:</p>
               <p>We muſt not burn a <hi>Samaritan</hi> becauſe he will not turn Jew; neither muſt we deſtroy men, becauſe they will not be proſelited to our Opinions; the Jews muſt not call for fire from Heaven upon the Samaritans, becauſe they Worſhip not with them at the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> nor the <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> refuſe to give entertainment to the <hi>Jews,</hi> becauſe they do not worſhip with them upon <hi>Mount Girizim.</hi> Herein our Saviour was a great pattern of moderation, forbearance and brotherly kindneſs; and his Goſpel is not <hi>Evangelium Armatum,</hi> an Armed Goſpel; it is <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s, and not Chriſts way to propagate Religion by the ſword; Prayers and Tears, and Sufferings, and Faſtings, and Alms deeds, and Love, and Charity, are thoſe Forces by which Chriſtian Religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo victorious and triumphant in the World.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Ab utilitate;</hi> It is profitable to bear with our diſſenting Brethren.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. It's beſt for the Church.</item>
                  <item>2. It's beſt for the State.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. For the Church; There is a twofold Unity; an Unity in Judgement, and that's <hi>Truth;</hi> an Unity in Affection, and that's <hi>Love:</hi> If we cannot obtain the firſt, we may the latter; if we cannot have an Unity in Truth, we may by this means have an Unity in Love: It is yeelded, and need not be made the ſubject of any mans Diſpute, That Hereſies are damnable and pernicious; but ſince as the Scriptures ſpeak, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 19. <hi>There must be Hereſies alſo amongſt you;</hi> not becauſe that God ordained them to be, for he cannot decree ſin; but becauſe he permitted them, and ſaw they would be held and maintained in the Church; as the <hi>Aſtronomer</hi> prognoſticates an Eclipſe either of the Sun or Moon, not that he hath any influence upon thoſe Heavenly Bodies, to cauſe the leaſt change or alteration; but becauſe by the Rules of his Art
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118624:21"/> he ſees ſuch and ſuch things will happen: We ought to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s advice unto <hi>Titus,</hi> 3. 10. An Heretick after the firſt and ſecond admonition, reject.</p>
               <p>Hereſie it is the mutilation and maiming of ſome of the principal branches of Chriſtian Faith, and this pertinaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly defended and maintained contrary to the reproof and cenſure of a lawful Authority: But as for thoſe leſs differences in Religion, and ſince there will always be ſuch amongſt us, (for faces do not more vary then underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and conceptions) it is beſt (for the preſervation of the Churches peace, love and unity) that we bear with, and exerciſe a wonderful lenity towards thoſe that diſſent from us, that we do not preſently excommunicate, unchurch and deliver one another up unto Satan for every difference in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion and judgement: We complain much of the want of Love, of that hatred, malice, and jealouſie that we finde ſtirred up amongſt the preſent Goſpellers and Profeſſors in Religion; me-thinks it ſhould be with us the Students in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, as it is with thoſe Students and Proficients in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy at the Univerſity, who though they do often diſpute their Opinions <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> in the Schools and Halls, yet do they love one another nevertheleſs, though one be for <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> another for <hi>Ramus,</hi> a third for <hi>Zeno,</hi> a fourth for <hi>Epicurus,</hi> yet doth it not occaſion the leaſt animoſity, breach or diſ-affection. We all acknowledge one God, the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from the dead, ſalvation by Jeſus Chriſt, future re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and puniſhments, the neceſſity of Virtue, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Holineſs; that no man hath power of himſelf to do any thing that good is; that all grace, ſtrength and ſuffic en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy are of God: Theſe are every mans Conceſſions; neither do I know any man living that does ſo much as diſpute or queſtion the truth of them: We agree in the greater, why do we differ in the leſs? How much would it make for the Church, its peace, encreaſe and enlargement, could we give unto one another ſome few Granes of Allowance in this caſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is beſt for the State, for the ſettlement of the peace and proſperity thereof. This I offer to humble conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118624:21"/> there wants nothing ſo much to make us happy and glorious, as mercifulneſs one unto another; there is nothing more tender then a mans conſcience; the Graſhopper is a burden to it; thoſe that will ſuffer others to touch them in their Eſtates, to touch them in their Dignity and Greatneſs, both which are very dear to them, will not endure to be touched in their conſciences: This hath broken us ſo oft in pieces, that men are not content to ſecure their own Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an libetty, unleſs it be with the infringement of othet mens: May the Princes and Magiſtrates of this World (to uſe the expreſſion of a ſober perſon) take heed of coming too near that Mount which <hi>Jehovah</hi> hath ſanctified for himſelf, and for his Son Jeſus to ſet their Thrones on. We are for peace and ſettlement, and that upon ſuch a <hi>Baſis</hi> as may ſtand to the good liking both of God and men, till he come who ſhall call in the Commiſſions of all the Kings and Rulers of the Earth; may the foundations therefore be laid in Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Juſtice, Righteouſneſs, Moderation, that the glory of our Nation may grow up in Renown.</p>
               <p>The Conſciences and Judgements of men, are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Territories and Dominions of Chriſt; whoſoever ſhall enter by any other Authority then this, upon theſe Sacred Demeans, intrencheth upon anothers Right.</p>
               <p>I paſſe this Uſe with theſe following Limitations.</p>
               <p>In general, by what hath been ſpoken, we do not ſeek to infringe the Magiſtrate's juſt Power, or to leſſen his duty, as he is a Chriſtian, we willingly yeild him the dignity of being Gods Deputy, and if he pleaſe, <hi>Cuſtos utriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tabulae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That they vouchſafe to ſee to the obſervation of the Lords Day, not onely that men forbear their Callings, but alſo that they come to Church, or ſuch places of Worſhip where Divine Service is performed, that under a pretence of Liberty of Conſcience, men take not an occaſion to tranſgreſs the Laws of ſobriety and holineſs; For were this Lords Day an Ordinance onely of man, it becomes every man to ſubmit to it for the Lords ſake.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That nothing that hath been ſpoken extend to deter the Magiſtrate from puniſhing ſwearing, profanation of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118624:22"/> Lords Name, all immodeſty, and violation of the Laws of Nature; for theſe are things that all men have agreed in, as worthy of puniſhment; and if there were no warrant from the Word of God, yet <hi>volenti non ſit injuria;</hi> he that is willing hath no injury done him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Nay, I would even ſubſcribe to puniſh blaſphemy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Judicial Law, if there were any perſons law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully appointed, who could infallibly determine.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Br.</hi> Let us imitate the mercifulneſs of God in pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Injuries, and forgiving offences one againſt another; let us take out our Saviour's Leſſon, <hi>Let us pray for our enemies, do good to thoſe that hate us, ſo ſhall we heap coals of fire upon their heads.</hi> But alas! how far are we from this God-like temper? Every man almoſt ſeeks to be <hi>Deus ultionem,</hi> a god of revenge. We write favours and benefits on the Sand, but injuries in Marble, never to be blotted out. Though we crave and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect all forgiveneſs from Heaven daily, yet we exerciſe very little upon the Earth: Inſtead of extenuating one anothers offences, we heighten and aggravate them in our bills of debts and treſpaſſes; for fifties we write hundreds, and for hundreds, thouſands. As God is prone to forgive, ſo we are to take revenge one upon another; I wiſh there were not that occaſion for me to tell you how much you are unlike unto God.</p>
               <p>For pity, lo cruelty; for love, envy, hatred and iealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; and for pardon, behold revenge; every man ſtudies the Law of Retaliation, to return like for like, which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour expreſly abrogated, <hi>Matthew</hi> 5. 38. Let me borrow an Apoſtrophe.</p>
               <p>O cruel Revenge, of a venomous and dangerous maligni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which filleth the heart with Plagues, the life with Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and the World with Tragedies: What havock doſt thou make, what flames doſt thou kindle, unleſs Grace and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon give ſome temper and alleviation. A ſpirit from beneath, raiſed from Hell, injurious to civil Society, pernicious to States and Kingdoms, kindled by pride, nouriſhed by flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, ſharpened by inſolent Tongues, which makes their lives a continual crime, and their memories that exerciſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118624:22"/> it, a perpetual execration. Chriſtians! what ſhall I now ſay farther to perſwade you to Moderation, Clemency, Pardon, Forgiveneſs? If the example of God, the pattern of Chriſt the practiſe of the moſt eminent Saints; If this will not do it, what will? Onely let me re-mind you of that great day which is ready to dawn upon the world, when the Judge of heaven and earth ſhall come riding upon the clouds with ten thouſand Angells in his company, and ſhall take his ſeat in the air, when that general Aſſize ſhal be kept, wee ſhal all come to hold up our hands for mercy at his Bar. Let me tell you from God, in whoſe name I now propheſie unto you, that unleſs you here diſplay the enſigns of your mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on earth, neither will God hold forth the Scepter of his mercy and pardon unto that day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>3ly.</hi> Let us imitate God in his bounty and liberality, (that I may ſpeak a word for the poor) <hi>who cauſeth the Sun to ſhine, and the rain to fall, both upon the juſt and the unjuſt.</hi> I ſpeak now to the rich, thè great and mighty in this world, <hi>You</hi> live upon the alms of heaven, ſubſiſt by divine bounty, and are maintained at his coſt and charge: he keepeth a plentiful houſe, and hath made large pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for <hi>You,</hi> onely in the diſpoſition of things, he hath left the poor to be taken care of by the rich. <hi>The poor, ſaies our Lord and Saviour, yee have alwaies with you; me ye have not alwaies:</hi> that what love we feel in our hearts unto Jeſus Chriſt, we might expreſs unto our indigent brethren for his ſake. <hi>To do good therefore, and to communicate, forget not, for with ſuch ſacrifices</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>God is well pleaſed.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſome men have taken up a Religion that excuſes them from all acts of bounty, goodneſs, and charity, yet the Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 12. makes Charity, or mercy to be a peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar ſign and character of God's Elect: <hi>Put on therefore as the Elect of God,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>bowels of pities and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let me therefore give you that advice which was given to <hi>Nebuchadnezar, Dan.</hi> 4. 27. <hi>That you break off your ſins by righteouſneſs, and your iniquities by ſhewing mercy to the poor:</hi> be daily caſting in of your abundance into this treaſury of God: Make unto <hi>your ſelves bags that wax not old; ſo ſhall you have treaſure in heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:118624:23"/>
               <p> Let us not be lifte the hypocritical Jewes, who faſted for ſtrife and debate, and to ſmite with the fiſt of wickedneſs, and even then when they made long praiers, devour'd wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows houſes; but rather like the good Centurion, <hi>Act.</hi> 19. that not <hi>onely our praiers,</hi> but <hi>our Alms and Charity may come up in remembrance before God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we have finiſhed the firſt Uſe, by way of <hi>imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2ly. By way of Conſolation; if our heavenly Father be ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful:</hi> Are any of us made ſenſible of our great miſcarria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and how unſuitably we have acted, to the genious and Spirit of Chriſt and the Goſpel: Do we recollect how often we have violated his righteous Laws, tranſgreſſed his holy precepts, abuſed his mercies, againſt <hi>the light of nature,</hi> againſt <hi>the light of grace.</hi> This Doctrine adminiſters great Conſolation; that we have to to do with God, and not with men; with God, whoſe mercies are infinite; and not with men, whoſe mercies are cruelties.</p>
               <p>This is the greateſt comfort that can poſſibly be laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, in all our ſoul-conflicts: That our God is a lover of ſouls; that the lives of his creatures are very dear and pretious in his ſight, and next unto his own Juſtice, which is himſelf, we are conſiderable with him. It was a great comfort to the Syrian King, and his Nobles, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20. 31. that they heard <hi>the Kings of the houſe of Iſrael were merciful Kings,</hi> this was the great incouragement of Addreſs, a motive to humiliation upon hopes of acceptance: We have allheard that God is a merciful God, a tender and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Prince: Let it move us to put on the garment of true humiliation, and make our ſolemne and penitential Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes unto him, <hi>That he may pardon our ſin, and remember our iniquities no more.</hi> To conclude; Let us not preſume up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the mercies of God, ſo as to turn his Grace into wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs; to take Arguments of Sinning from the conſidera-of Divine mercy; that becauſe <hi>mercy abounds,</hi> therefore we make <hi>ſin to abound;</hi> this were ill to requite the Lord; and <hi>know,</hi> that by how much the mercies of God have been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, by ſo much will the wrath and the diſpleaſure of God be encreaſed againſt us, if we abuſe them.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:118624:23"/>
            <head>Books worth Buying.</head>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>THe <hi>Banner of Juſtification displayed;</hi> or a Diſcourſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the deep and important Myſterie of the <hi>Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of a ſinner,</hi> wherein the ſeveral cauſes thereof, being both numerous &amp; various, are from firſt to laſt diligently inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after, and their ſeveral contributions towards ſo great and happy a work, clearly diſtinguiſhed, and aſſigned to their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cauſes <hi>(reſpectively:)</hi> By Mr. <hi>John Goodwin;</hi> newly come forth.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Triumviri;</hi> Or the Genius, Spirit, and Deportment of the three Men, Mr. <hi>Richard Resbury,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Pawſon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>George Kendall,</hi> in their late Writings againſt the Free Grace of God in the redemption of the World, and vouchſafement of means of ſalvation unto men; briefly deſcribed in their native and true colours, borrowed of themſelves in their Writings (reſpectively.) Together with ſome brief touches (in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face) upon Dr. <hi>John Owen,</hi> Mr. <hi>Thomas Lamb</hi> (of the <hi>Spittle)</hi> Mr. <hi>Jeans,</hi> Mr. <hi>Obadiah How,</hi> and Mr: <hi>Marchamond Needham,</hi> in relation to their late Writings againſt the Author: In <hi>Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> by Mr: <hi>John Goodwin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Tryers and Ejectors of Miniſters, tryed and caſt, by the Laws of God and men: By <hi>Iohn Goodwin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mercy in her Exaltation;</hi> a Sermon preached at the Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of Mr. <hi>Daniel Tarlor;</hi> by Mr. <hi>John Goodwin:</hi> In <hi>Quarte.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Natural Mans Caſe ſtated; Or an exact Map of the little World, Man; in 17. Sermons; by Mr. <hi>Chriſtopher Love:</hi> To which is added a Sermon preached at his Funeral, by Mr. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Manton</hi> of <hi>Newington.</hi> In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Comment on <hi>Ruth;</hi> together with two Sermons, one tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching how to live wel, the other minding all how to dye well: By <hi>Thomas Fuller,</hi> Author of the <hi>Holy State.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:118624:24"/>
                  <item> Goſpel publick Worſhip; Or the Tranſlation, Metaphraſe, Analyſis, and Expoſition of <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. from <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. to 8. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing the compleat Pattern of Goſpel Worſhip.</item>
                  <item>Alſo an Expoſition of the 18. Chapter of <hi>Matthew,</hi> to which is added, A diſcovery of <hi>Adams</hi> threefold eſtate in Paradiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Moral, Legal, and Evangelical, by <hi>Thomas Brewer:</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Grand Enquiry who is the righteous man, by <hi>William Moore</hi> at <hi>Whaley</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Declaration of the Judgement of <hi>Iames Arminius,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Election and Reprobation; tranſlated into Engliſh by <hi>Tobias Conyers.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>An <hi>Idea,</hi> or body of Church-Diſcipline in the Theorick and Practick, by Mr. <hi>Rogers:</hi> in <hi>quarto.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lucas Redivivus,</hi> Or the Goſpel-phyſician, preſcribing (by way of Meditation) Divine phyſick to prevent Diſeaſes not yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred upon the ſoul, by <hi>Iohn Anthony,</hi> Dr. in <hi>Phyſick,</hi> in <hi>quarto.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Letter of Addreſs to the late Protector <hi>Oliver,</hi> by <hi>D. F.</hi> alias, <hi>Tobias Conyers;</hi> in quarto.</item>
                  <item>The Return of Mercies, or the Saints advantage by loſſes. By Mr. <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> in 12.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118624:24"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
